Let's be clear, man. When somebody
dropped the line that Africans sold
Africans, best believe they trying to
justify a anti-black history in a way
that gives receipts for your oppression
and don't allow for you to challenge it.
Africans selling Africans to slavery is
a empirical attempt to erase how white
folks uniquely benefited from enslaving
black people. Nowhere in the world do we
try to justify violence or suffering of
a people by saying, "Well, these people
kill each other, so why can't nobody
else do it?" Today, we're dissecting the
complicity myth. You know, the
complicity myth, the viral persuasive
way of saying that black people are
equally responsible for engaging in the
Atlantic slave trade. You know, the one
that mystifies power and distinctions
between being a prisoner of war, being a
debt prisoner, being a denture servant,
and being in child slavery. You know
that one right there. The argument
typically goes like because some African
elites engaged in the Atlantic slave
trade, this means that black people are
equally
responsible for the African slave trade
or it's just used as a way to silence or
to disarm any type of accountability or
acknowledgements that white people did
some bad things. Let's be clear. When
somebody dropped the African soul,
Africans line, it's definitely serving
as a gotcha moment that's supposed to
silence your ass from talking about
reparations, white supremacy, or white
accountability. And it also comes as a
disingenuous way of being able to
homogenize different African tribes by
saying and fabricating this contemporary
idea of the pan-African identity to be
able to say, well, because the Euroba
was selling the Mafa tribe, this means
that Africans are selling Africans. And
you know, we never talk about that when
it comes to uh Germany invading Poland.
We don't say white people invading white
people. We see them as being two
different sovereign nations and we see
it as being different tribes and
identities. But somehow when it comes to
black folks doing black folks, it's
always a way to say black folks did it
to each other. So why are you mad about
this? Or you should do something about
first how black folks do it to each
other before you even address how other
people do it to black people. And it's
just like, bro, what the hell you
talking about? This is what it look
like.
It looks like white people telling black
people to shut the hell up because
Africans sold Africans into slavery.
What it looks like is black Republicans
trying to save their masses from
responsibility or criticism and saying
you can't get mad at masses because your
own people sold your own people. In this
complicity myth, we're always able to
take the way that a Europeans are
complicit in waging violence against
each other and oppressing each other.
And we don't see it as white-on-white
crime. We don't see it as white people
killing white people. For World War I
and World War II, we normalize the way
in which white folks [__] up white
folks. And we never use it as
justification to say, "Well, you can't
be mad at these people [__] over
white people. You can't be mad these
people messing over white people because
white people mess up people, too." U
Newton said that power is the ability to
define a phenomenon and make it act in a
desired manner. And the phenomenon we're
getting in today is the complicity myth,
man. the complicity myth that you see
all in these viral videos, that you see
in the halfbaked uh uh history rooms,
that you see in the pseudoextual comment
sections of the Facebook pages, all the
various ways to try to disarm black
people when it comes to white supremacy,
accountability, and reparations. Man,
what this means for us as black people
is that it is a psychological trap of
trauma. one that gets us to internalize
anti-blackness that says that because
Africans sold you into slavery, this
means you can't be critical with the
economy that was built on your back.
Shout out to King Cotton. Oh man, today
we dissecting how people shucking Jive
when it comes to talking about history,
specifically when they trying to
rationalize with slavery and trying to
center that because Africans sold
Africans into slavery. This means you
better not say [__] about the people of
European descent uniquely benefiting
from it because hey, your people did it
in the first place. Hey, when person A
stiff from person B and get a person C,
should person C give the stolen [__]
Usually what it is, even in terms of the
hood, if these white folks know you are
willingly buying from a booster, I know
it's Christmas time. It's going to be a
lot of people hitting up their fellow
boosters and talking about, "Hey, can
you get this? Can you get that?" It is
illegal to buy illegally possessed [__]
You feel me? This this this this video
I'mma show y'all is this dude that loves
to use his black bravado, his black
masculinity, his ability to try to be
cool AND SCREAM AND HOLL and all this
old [__] to appeal to white folks. You
know what I'm saying? He's shucking and
jing. He being an anti-lack apologist
that's sympathizing and white supremacy
in the way to make it way individually
benefits at the at the expense of the
collective. What we would call being a
sellout or what some people would call
being an Uncle Tom, but I don't like to
use it that way. White people got some
nerve convincing half the world that
we're violent. The same racist ancestor
that captured and tormented my ancestor
for profit.
>> Stop looking past the fact that they
bought your mother. They ain't
oppressing slave and capture your MOTHER
ASS. THEY BOUGHT YOU FROM THE OTHER
[__] THAT WAS SELLING YOU.
Y'ALL KEEP TRYING TO FORGET THE FACT
THAT AFRICA HAD SLAVES. THEY SOLD THEIR
SLAVES.
WHAT PART YOU AIN'T GETTING?
>> RIGHT HERE IS AN ILLUSTRATION of what I
was talking about when I say what it
looks like. It looks like a person
shucking and jing at the expense of
black people's dignity and being able to
mystify slavery to try to appeal to
white folks. I'mma use my portable
skills as being a African-American
studies major. You know what I'm saying?
Getting my little old degree and just
talking about how it is empirically
false to say that Africans sold Africans
into slavery as being the full picture.
This is a psychological trap that's
designed to get us to internalize our
ancestors oppression as being their
fault. For everybody else, it's an
intellectual pacifier to baby y'all into
anti-blackness, to literally feed y'all
on a semi lack of anti-blackness to make
it where when y'all grow up to be
intellectual adults, some of y'all still
be childish than hell, you still buy
into the pacification of saying white
folks didn't do anything. For everybody
else, it serves as an intellectual
pacifier to absolve them from thinking
about slavery in a way that the very
life they live, the material reality
that they exist in was made possible
through slavery in a world that's
situated on capitalism. We always talk
about the distribution of wealth and how
things are passed down from generation
to generation to generation to
generation to generation. All
descendants of enslaved peoples always
think about the way we have not been
given [__] That's why we talk about
reparations. But the descendants of the
slave master and the overseers, they
don't never want to be blamed for the
past, but they always want to hold on to
the [__] their ancestors left them from
the past. This is one of those other
trick of times. It's a surface level
argument. It's simple. See, it was a
business transaction. Everybody was
guilty. Get over it. It framed the
entire continent of Africa as a
monolith. It reduces the most
catastrophic force migration in human
history. If you don't believe so, I will
burn your ass in the debate to a simple
act of tribal betrayal. It ignores the
scale, the technology, the ideology, and
the purpose of the European-driven
system versus existing limited practice
and servitude in Africa. It is
intellectually dishonest and
disingenuous to try to say that the uh
reality that black people will be
subject to or the African people will be
subject to on that boat in the new world
is what the African people knew they was
getting into. As well as disingen what
to try to say because there are certain
instances and I'm not denying that there
were African elites that sold black
people or that sold their own people or
they sold rivalry tribes into slavery.
There are also different African
leadership, different African king and
queens that fought directly against the
enslavement of Europeans.
So to try to make it like it was all
this, it's some shucking and jing
bootlicking [__] I remember
watching a great series called
Underground.
And in underground, it was this
light-skinned brother that was a a a a a
enslaved person as well that made a a
career out of being a slave catcher as
well as engaging in trying to appeal to
the master always at the at the expense
of people that was enslaved on the
plantation. Even though [__] that I
showed y'all love to try to talk about
who set up slavery and who should get
off the plantation, what he doing in
this video in the video I just showed
y'all is him acting exactly like that
slave own underground that was always
pedalling doing business for white
supremacy at the expense of the [__]
he was around. There's no way for you to
say y'all keep on forgetting that [__]
sold [__] till they weren't oppressing
you. Man, listen man. If you buy some
crack from one person and you sell it to
the other person, is these white folks
gonna say it's not your fault, it ain't
no issue because you bought the crack
from somebody else. No. This how I know
y'all be being purposely disingenuous.
You purposely obtuse when you try to
talk about, well, black people sold
black people into slavery and you can't
be you trying to reduce one of the most
catastrophic dehumanizations in world
history for what?
to appeal to the ethics and morals of
white folks.
Couldn't be me, man. Couldn't be me.
This little myth people engage in only
further serves racial global capitalism
that tries to sustain black suffering by
saying, "Hey, because African souls
Africans and African, this means
justifying endless exploitation and
profits on black suffering because, hey,
we ain't started." When I say global
racial capitalism, I mean an economic
order built on assigning a less than
human value to certain racial groups to
extract land and labor and cheaply as
possible. I would almost argue that
capitalism gets to define itself very
very specifically in the Americas based
off of slavery. How can I get the most
while giving the least? Nowadays we call
that lazy. Hey, when you hear the idea
that Africans sold Africans into
slavery, you got to ask the question,
how did Africans benefit from King
Cotton? When they talk about Africans,
southern Africans into slavery, they
make it as if African people were in
cahoots with the Europeans and was going
to benefit uniquely from the Europeans
being there. We don't want to get into
the manipulation. We don't want to get
into the abductions. We don't want to
get into the exploitation of how
different bodies was apprehended. When
we talk about African southern Africans
that glosses over all the unique
instances that wasn't like that when we
view Alex Haley when he writes roots he
does a a a he does some genealological
research and that's how we get the story
of Kainte who is abducted the way that
white folks and Europeans is able to
colonize and enslave in Africa during
the 1500s 1600s or whatever allow for
them to come back for the scramble of
Africa and then colonize Africa. So how
are you able to justify European
violence then when we talking about
power because you know this conversation
is one about power it's about who gets
what when where and how who get to
determine that [__] and we talk about
who had the power who had the navalmies
who had the infrastructure who had the
ability to manipulate the entire global
market is Europeans. This is how power
mystifies itself and how we let white
people and the Europeans get away of
creating entire worlds, entire countries
based off of the way they engage in thug
culture.
Today, human trafficking and abducting
people is bad. As a matter of fact,
today,
white people try to justify their part
of the white people and [__] like this
try to justify white people's
involvement within the entire training
ecosystem of human trafficking as a way
to say, "Well, because this ecosystem
already existed, then we shouldn't be,
man, stop playing." A historical
example, a receipt as one would put it
is King Zinga of Congo. Before I move
on, let's really just unpackage what we
just read and what King Alfonso exposes
when it comes to this narrative about
African southern Africans. It always
wants to paint our ancestors. that
always wants to paint different African
people as being passive, docile dumb
asses that was either inherently demonic
and was down for the selling of their
own people or some people that was just
stupid that didn't know better that just
laid down. You see, King Alfonso is an
example that shows that no, there
actually was resistance to European
enslavement and we have it documented.
No, everybody wasn't assimilating to the
way that Europeans was bringing over
talking about human cargo.
No, every slave that touched the boat
wasn't sold by another African.
Some of them were abducted and stolen.
This example should clear up that [__]
was just willingly saying, "Here you go.
Just hand them out. You don't know what
you're doing. Just giving them out."
Like just just showing this. It's false.
Queen of Zinga for over 30 years. She
led a military and diplomatic war
against these old Portuguese slave
traders. She formed a whole bunch of
different alliances because you know
solidarity and coalition building is
good with a whole bunch of different
rival powers. Showing y'all it was
already different ways of tribes to be
able to have a shared collective enemy.
You know what I'm saying? Even so much
of she was including rival powers of the
Dutch to fight against the Portuguese.
She was offering sanctuary to escape
slaves and train her army in guerrilla
warfare. She wasn't a collaborator. She
wasn't a middleman. Queen of Zinga is
one of the earliest fiercest
anti-colonial revolutionaries on the
African continent that should easily lay
to rest that because Africans sold
Africans, you better get to kiss these
white folks ass. What's another thing
too thing too? Y'all caught the part of
him saying that white folks bought your
ass from other Africans and then freed
you. This is a common way that I feel
like [__] love to lick the boots of
white folks while point without pointing
out who was white people fighting
against to free black people quote
unquote other white people. Get back
into the trick of time. [__] love to
spout this horrible product of American
education facts and saying that white
folks free black people first. Um
1803,
I believe it's over 60 years before
1865.
In 1803, the Haitian Revolution happened
where you had black people freeing
themselves from white servitude, from
white captivity.
And what we know is that after black
people freed themselves in 1803 in a
little island, St. Dominico or Haiti,
you know what I'm saying? That the slave
masters in America made sure we never
learned about it. Just like a lot of
y'all never learned about King Alfonso
or Queen Ozinga being active anti-
colonist being active anti-slavery. You
know what I'm saying? Anti take me to
being abolitionist. Damn. It's like,
man, y'all stop playing, man. On my papa
grave. Saying African sold Africans in
the 1700s is [__] It's finesse.
It's like saying the Europeans sold the
Europeans because the French king also
captured English soldiers. We don't
never say that. that white people
enslave white people because they was
bringing over indigent servants. We get
real specific when we start talking
about the delineations between what
white folks was doing to other white
folks and how they wasn't doing it to
black people. All of a sudden
distinctions matter. All of a sudden
delineating matter. When we start
talking about African, Southern
Africans, it's all homogeneous. It's all
monolithic. It's all the one story. When
you have the Highlanders and the
lowlanders beating up on each other in
Scotland, the entire world don't adopt
the perspective of lowlanders that the
Highlanders had. When we even when we
talk about the conflicts of the Irish or
the conflicts of any in any European any
European context, the entire world don't
adopt the perspective that one European
has over the other European. But that's
something that happened that's unique to
slavery. The entire world bought into
the idea that black equal slave. The
entire world bought into the idea that
enslaved people had no culture, no
language, no customs. And this justified
they suffering. When Africans, as quote
unquote, southern Africans, they're not
sitting as culturalist people. They're
not setting us as people that have no
customs and no language, no traditions.
But somehow that what becomes the
anti-lack misnomer or the anti-black
message, the dog whistle to the rest of
the world. When [__] start being
critical about power and white supremacy
and reparations, this will be getting
to. And there are certain people that
want to mystify because you believe
being able to stabilize the comfort zone
of white people is going to make you
where you benefit as an individual
that's literally selling out. That's
literally shucking and driving and being
a tongue. Uh let's say an organized
crime puts a gun to your head, kidnaps
your family, and forces you to sign over
a deed to your house at gunpoint. Then
they sell your [__] to a developer. Who
is guilty? The crime ring with the gun
or the developer who knowingly received
stolen property. Now imagine this [__]
400 years ago. The descendants of the
crime ring own half of the city built on
those stolen deeds. They point to you.
You're scared court signature and say,
"See, you sold it." They'll say it's a
fair transaction. We know it's not a
fair transaction. They'll say they not
responsible. We know they're
responsible. That's absurd. It's a crime
logic focusing on the sale or the
signature of the deliberate transaction
from the initial act of the armed
robbery and kidnapping. The power of the
gun. It's not ironic that the biggest
population of Africans outside of Africa
is in Brazil. Brazil is a Portuguese
colony. It's the reason why they speak
Portugal Portuguese there. It's the
reason why whether we're talking about
King Alfonso, Queen Azinga, both of them
had to deal with the Portuguese Empire
and how they were uniquely kidnapping
[__] As a matter of fact, to me, I
think about like this. White people were
willing to engage in some inhumane
[__] that would definitely go against
the social contract. If you believe that
they would just, well, uh, I want to
make sure before I pick up this negro
that I, uh, legitimately buy him and I
don't want to steal him. You smoking
dope and dog food. If you believe that
when [__] say African sold Africans
into slavery, it show that you have a
perspective of your people through the
eyes of white folks. It actually can
show that you don't see your people for
your own people, you see through the
eyes of white people. And that's the
reason why you're able to have this
homogeneous idea of [__] doing things
to each other. It's the idea that says
this, because I see the worst examples
of black people doing [__] to each
other, I'mma make black Republicans
responsible for that. That's the reason
why y'all love to disinel from the black
community, which is textbook
anti-blackness. The power of the gun,
the Portuguese warship, the British
musket is what made the sale possible.
That's what King Alfonso and Queen
Gazinga were fighting against. The
barrel of guns, not a free market. So,
some would say, should we just ignore
African complicity? Nope. I'm not saying
that. We should we should contextualize
it correctly, though. We should
contextualize it correctly while
acknowledging that there are African
nations that's complicit in slavery
that's doing something that's abstractly
different from all the European ones.
Not only are they trying to give
material ways to give retribution for
what they did like literally saying you
sorry part of the healing process and
restorative justice is what I'm saying
some scholars would say we should use
context and we should contextualize
correctly. We study it with the same
nuance that we apply European
collaborators with the Nazis. We don't
say Germans kill Jews to absolve Hitler.
We understand the system of Nazism, the
coercion, the ideology, and who
ultimately in charge. As a matter of
fact, when it even comes to Jewish
persecution, we know that Jew Jewish
people have been being [__] over since
the beginning of time. We don't say that
Hillary is justified in [__] over
Jews because people been doing it. We
never say that anti-semitism is
justifiable in America because it was
always it was already going. These are
all different ways of how we try to say
certain anti-black violence should be
justifiable or resationalized with
because it's been going on. It's been
going on. It's been going on. We must do
the same here. The focus must remain on
the architects of the system and not
those who were caught in this
destabilizing vortex. Another argument y
going to say is you just trying to make
white folks feel guilty and avoid black
accountability. As you can see, if you
being real and you're not being
purposely obtuse, within everything I
within the two examples I gave above,
they are both dealing with the
uniqueness and nuance of black people
being complicit while also making white
folks feel guilty. What blow my mind
about the concept of white guilt is that
in every other instance, the notion of
guilt is seen as being accountability.
It's seen as being responsibility. When
a judge asked my homeboy, my mom, my
daddy, are you guilty? and they say yes,
that is seen as something that's
supposed to be celebrated. But somehow
when you racialize guilt and put white
in front of it, all of a sudden notions
of guilt become bad. All of a sudden,
notions of guilt become a way for you to
weaponize responsibility and
accountability. That's crazy. Y'all
don't have that same issue when it comes
y'all criminalizing that courthouse.
Keep that same energy. Yeah, this about
accuracy though and not guilt. Accurate
history assigns accountability and
accountability is not the same as guilt.
its responsibility to understand how
this is engineered system created the
wealth gap, antilackness, policing and
the stereotypes we live with today.
Furthermore, black scholars in
communities still grapple with the
complex legacy of collaboration in
Africa. It's the reason why literature
bases like Afropesimism exists that
deals with how the entire world
including the African diaspora bought
into black equal enslaved and bought
into African-Americans and people in the
west the enslaved descendants of the
west being culturalist being without
language being without nation going
through what afropesimists say is nato
alienation going what afropesimists say
is complete dishonor these are all ways
and examples of how black scholars is
already dealing with and grappling with
the unique complex history and how the
entire world bought into the
dehumanization of particular peoples of
African descent. And it being real, the
idea that Africans sold Africans was
also used for white people to be able to
suture their guilt when it comes to what
they did in the scramble of Africa and
what they currently doing in the
continent of Africa. We see that
throughout the world. The idea that
[__] [__] up [__] is always used
to justify and further rationalize with
black suffering. Because if I can prove
that black people brought the suffering
of black people, too,
this means you can't be that mad at me
cuz everybody's doing it. I got kids and
as a father, that's some [__] that kids
say. As somebody used to be a nth and
10th grade English teacher, my students
would say, "Well, everybody's doing it."
When y'all say African South Africans,
that's what y'all doing. Y'all engaging
in ninth grade, 10th grade logic that
wants to be elusive and dance around
responsibility and accountability.
Anytime a kid say everybody's doing it,
they saying you shouldn't be that mad at
me cuz I ain't the only one. Really,
what it is is I done put these leather
pants on, bro. And [__] I felt like I
had to, you know, proverbally uh uh uh
step out on this [__] couch like Rick
James did on Dave Chappelle [__] You
feel me? I put these on because um I am
intellectually putting these leather
pants in this Jordan 11 foot down y'all
asses and I'm turning and I felt like
the leather pants would add a little
pizzazz to the intellectual analysis I'm
laying down on why y'all be lost in the
sauce of power and trying to make it as
if [__] just was inherently dumb or
inherently always looking to [__] each
other over. And this gets in the way of
how we have black unity because you're
always able to create a reality that
says we never had black unity even
before the beginning of the time. And we
don't get to think about how there are
maroon communities. We don't think about
how there was a bunch of solidarity
amongst the diaspora throughout the
diaspora. Regardless of what these white
folks want to tell you, these white
folks will give us a narrative to
justify what they did to make sure we
don't do it to them. Insidious, right?
Conflictual, right? That's really what
it is. And when you have black people
that parrot white conservative speaking
points and they do it in a way where
they think they being intellectual, not
only is it a slap in our face, to me, it
reflects their character,
it reflects who raised them. And a lot
of them just need to go to therapy. A
lot of y'all are suffering from a
childhood where other black people maybe
questioned, negotiated, created
authenticity tests about your blackness.
and I was an adult. You're trying to
compensate for the way that the child in
you wants to prove they are black
enough. Or for some of y'all, y'all gave
up the idea of trying to be black enough
because you got tired of being
trivialized because of the trauma and
the stress. I'm not not negating on and
you decided you was going to always try
to appeal to white folks instead of
negotiating about this. I rather be the
black Republican. It's funny to me that
the very black Republicans that always
talk about why everything got to be
about race, they love to sensationalize
their race in relationship to being a
conservative say, "I ain't like them
[__] over there." People sold black
people into slavery is used as a racist
trope to always making sure that we have
distrust around black leadership and
always make sure that we are skeptical
around black unity because if [__] was
messing up with [__] then, what do I
expect for them now? So when you hear
this [__] like this, don't get stuck in
debating the sliver of our argument or
the sliver of a truth or the sliver of,
you know what I'm saying, what happened
historically. Account for the entirety
of how history works, specifically when
it comes to black involvement or African
involvement within slavery. The African
identity wasn't one that existed before
European enslavers got there. is one
that ensla European enslavers inscribe
the African identity onto the constant
to justify their enslavement. That's
very important. Even the homogenized
idea of you black and non-black, that is
a idea that the colonizer that the
enslavery that the European brought over
to the continent to justify and
rationalize ethically with what they
were doing to make it way business is
business, man. African sold Africans or
European sold Africans. Everybody was
selling Africans. It's okay.
Yeah, when you hear this, don't get
stuck in debating the truth. Reframe the
question. Ask who designed the system,
who financed it, who provided the
ideology of racism to justify it, who
today holds the most wealth and power
that that system extracted. All these
going to point to the same people
because, you know, always asking the
questions of who and how always gets the
conversation going a little bit further.
I always make it so where we can go a
little bit deeper in something instead
of putting a more breath in something
because you know it's always depth over
breath shot to my debate people. Shift
the demand from admit guilt to pursue
accountability. Accountability looks
like supporting rigorous history
education honest institutional audits
and yes reparative justice. It means
recognizing that the crime wasn't just a
sale, but the entire century's worth of
project of racial capitalism that
justified anti-black violence and
manipulated
a bunch of people in the world to buy in
to the servitude and suffering of black
folks. This racial capitalism, this
global racial capitalism that some were
manipulated into, but the others were
willfully created and proliferated from
and still do. This is research of a me
search where I try to uplift your
vocabulary and ways of thinking about
yourself in the world. Education is
elevation. Until next time, um,
subscribe to the Substack channel if you
want access to any of these examples
that I have or get more into the
readings that's referenced in this as
well as having a nice good faith
conversation about slavery, who's
responsible for slavery, who benefited
the most from slavery, and how slavery
ideas still evolve today, how they still
go to the day.